- Hi, I'm Tim Berglund with Confluent.
I'd like to tell you what Apache Kafka is.
But first, I wanna start
with some background.
For a long time now,
we have written programs
that store information in databases.
Now, what databases encouraged us to do,
is to think of the world
in terms of things,
things like I don't know, users,
and maybe a thermostat,
that's a thermometer
but you get the idea.
Maybe a physical thing like a train,
let's say a train, things,
there are things in the world
database encourages thinking those terms,
and those things have some state,
we take that state, we
store it in the database.
This has worked well for decades.
But now some people are finding
that it's better rather than
thinking of things first,
to think of events first.
Now events have some state too, right?
An event has a description
of what happened with it.
But the primary idea is that,
the event is an indication in time
that the thing took place.
Now it's a little bit cumbersome
to store events in databases,
instead, we use a structure called a log.
And a log is just an ordered
sequence of these events,
an event happens and
we write it into a log,
a little bit of state,
a little bit of description what happens.
And that says, hey, that
event happened at that time.
As you can see, logs are
really easy to think about,
they're also easy to build at scale,
which historically has not
quite been true of databases,
which have been a little cumbersome
in one way or another to build at scale.
Apache Kafka is the system
for managing these logs,
using a fairly standard historical term,
it calls them topics, this is a topic.
A topic is just an ordered
collection of events
that are stored in a durable way,
durable meaning that
they're written to disk,
and they're replicated,
so they're stored on more than one disk
on more than one server,
somewhere wherever that
infrastructure runs,
so that there's no one hardware failure
that can make that data go away.
Topics can store data for
a short period of time,
like a few hours, or days, or years,
or hundreds of years or indefinitely.
Topics can also be relatively small,
or they can be enormous.
There's nothing about the
economics of Kafka that says
that topics have to be large
in order for it to make sense,
and there's nothing about
the architecture of Kafka
that says that they have to stay small,
so they can be small, they can be big,
they can remember data forever,
they can remember data
just for a little while.
But there are persistent record of events.
Each one of those events represents
a thing happening in the
business like remember a user,
maybe a user updates her shipping address,
or a train, unloads cargo,
or a thermostat reports
that the temperature has gone from comfy
to is it getting hot in here.
Each one of those things can
be an event stored in a topic,
and Kafka encourages you
to think of events first,
and things second.
Now, back when databases ruled the world,
it was kind of a trend to
build one large program,
we'll just build this
gigantic program here
that uses one big database all by itself.
And it was customary for a
number of reasons to do this,
but these things grew to a point
where they were difficult to change,
and also difficult to think about.
They got too big for any one developer
to fit that whole program
in his or her head
at the same time.
And if you've lived like this,
you know that that's true.
Now the trend is to write lots
and lots of small programs,
each one of which is small enough
to fit in your head and think
about and version and change
and evolve all on its own.
And these things can talk to each other
through Kafka topics.
So each one of these services
can consume the message
from a Kafka topic, do
whatever its computation is,
that goes on in there,
and then produce that message
off to another Kafka topic
that lives over here.
So that output is now durably,
and maybe even permanently
recorded for other services
and other concerns in
the system to process.
So with all this data
living in these persistent
real time streams,
and I've drawn two of them now,
but imagine there are dozens
or hundreds more in a large system.
Now it's possible to build new services
that perform real time
analysis of that data.
So I can stand up some
other service over here,
that does some kind of gauge,
some sort of real time
analytics dashboard.
And that is just consuming
messages from this topic here,
that's in contrast to
the way it used to be
where you ran a batch process overnight.
Now, it's possible that yesterday
is a long time ago for
some businesses now.
You might want that insight to be instant
or as close to instant
as it could possibly be.
And with data in these topics
as events that get processed
as soon as they happen.
It's now fairly straightforward
to build these services
that can do that analysis
in real time.
So you've got events, you've got topics,
you've got all these little services
talking to each other through topics,
you got real time analytics.
I think if you have those
four things in your head,
you've got a decent idea
of kind of the minimum
viable understanding
not only of what Kafka is,
which is this distributed log thing,
but also of the kinds of
software architectures
that Kafka tends to give rise to.
When people start building systems on it,
this is what happens.
Once a company starts using Kafka,
it tends to have this viral effect, right?
We've got these persistent
distributed logs
that are records of the
things that have happened,
we've got things talking through them,
but there are other systems.
I mean, what's this,
there's this database,
there's probably gonna be, you know,
another database out there that was built,
before Kafka came along,
and you wanna integrate these systems.
There could be other systems entirely,
maybe there's a search cluster,
maybe you use some SAS product
to help your sales people
organize their efforts, all
these systems in the business,
and their data isn't in Kafka.
Well, Kafka Connect is a tool
that helps get that data in,
and back out,
when there's all these
other systems in the world,
you wanna collect data, so
changes happen in a database,
and you wanna collect that data
and get it written into a topic like that.
And now, I can stand up some new service
that consumes that data,
and does whatever computation is on it,
now that it's in a Kafka
topic, that's the whole point,
Connect gets that data in,
then that service produces some result,
which goes to a new topic over here.
And connect is the piece that moves it
to whatever that external
legacy system is here.
So Kafka Connect is this process
that does this inputting
and this outputting,
and it's also an ecosystem of connectors.
There are dozens, even
hundreds of connectors
out there in the world, some
of them are open source,
some of them are commercial,
some of them are in between,
but they're these little pluggable modules
that you can deploy,
to get this integration
done in a declarative way,
you deploy them, you configure them,
you don't write code, to do
this reading from the database,
this writing to whatever
that external system is.
Those modules already exist,
the code's already written,
you just deploy them and
Connect does that integration
to those external systems.
And let's think about the
work that these things do,
these services, these boxes I'm drawing,
they have some life of their
own, they're programs, right?
But they're gonna process
messages from topics,
and they're gonna have some computation
that they wanna do over those messages.
And it's amazing, there's
really just a few things
that people end up doing, like, say,
you have messages, these green messages,
you wanna group all those up
and add some field,
like come up with total weight
of all the train cars
that past a certain point or something,
but only a certain kind of car,
only the green kinds of cars.
And then you've got these other,
say, you've got these orange ones here.
So right away we see that,
we're gonna have to go
through those messages,
we're gonna have to group by some key,
and then we'll take the group
and run some aggregation over it,
or maybe count them or
something like that.
Maybe you want to filter,
maybe I've got this topic,
and let's see, make some room
for some other topic over here
that's got some other kind of data.
And I wanna take all the messages here,
and somehow link them with
messages in this topic,
and enrich when I see this,
this message happened here,
I wanna go enrich it with the data
that's in this other topic.
These are common things,
if the first time you thought about it,
that might seem unusual,
but those things grouping, aggregating,
filtering, enrichment.
Enrichment, by the way,
it goes by another name and
database, that's a joint, right?
These are the things that
these services are going to do.
They're simple in principle
to think about and to sketch,
but to actually write the
code to make all that happen,
takes some work and that's
not work you wanna do.
So Kafka, again, in the box,
just like it has Connect
for doing data integration,
it has an API called Kafka streams.
That's a Java API that handles
all of the framework and infrastructure
and kind of kind of undifferentiated stuff
you'd have to build to get that work done.
So you can use that as a
Java API, in your services,
and get all that done in a
scalable and fault tolerant way,
just like we expect for modern
applications to be able to do
and that's not framework
code you have to write,
you just get to use it
because you're using Kafka.
Now if you're a developer
and you wanna learn more,
you know, the thing to do,
is to start writing code.
Check those things out,
let us know if you have any questions
and I hope we hear from you soon.
(upbeat music)